A Finding Aid to the Nancy Goldring Papers, circa 1950-2015, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Nancy Goldring papers
circa 1950-2020
Archives of American Art
Goldring, N. (Nancy)
AAA.goldnanc
Archival Resource Key
5.1 Linear feet
0.213 Gigabytes
The papers of New York artist Nancy Goldring measure 5.1 linear feet and 0.213 GB and date from circa 1950-2020. Her career and personal life are documented through biographical material; personal and professional correspondence; writings; project and exhibition files; printed and digital material; scrapbooks; atwork; and photographic material. Notable correspondents include Lawrence Alloway, Robert Lax, and Leo Steinberg. There is a 0.4 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2020 that includes printed material, artwork, correspondence (emails, handmade cards), poetry, photographs of friends and family, and misc. Materials date from circa 1967-2020.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Nancy Goldring donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in 2015 and 2021.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York artist Nancy Goldring measure 5.1 linear feet and 0.213 GB and date from circa 1950-2020. Her career and personal life are documented through biographical material; personal and professional correspondence; writings; project and exhibition files; printed and digital material; scrapbooks; artwork; and photographic material. Notable correspondents include Lawrence Alloway, Robert Lax, and Leo Steinberg.There is a 0.4 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated in 2020 that includes printed material, artwork, correspondence (emails, handmade cards), poetry, photographs of friends and family, and misc. Materials date from circa 1967-2020.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical / Historical
Nancy Goldring (1945- ) is an American artist working in New York. Raised in St. Louis, Missouri where her father was a professor of cardiology at Washington University, Goldring attended Smith College, receiving a BA in art history in 1967. She spent a year in Italy on a Fulbright fellowship and was later enrolled in the MFA program at New York University. She has been teaching at Montclair State University since the early 1970s. In 1994, Goldring traveled in India and Sri Lanka on another Fulbright fellowship.
In 1969, Goldring co-founded SITE (Sculpture in the Environment) with several other artists interested in developing public art projects. Within a few years, Goldring moved on to explore other forms of artmaking and subsequently developed a technique she calls "foto-projection" which combines photography, drawing, models, and slide projection. She is influenced by travel, location, memory.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as nine series
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1957-2014 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1962-2015 (1.2 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1955-2014 (0.3 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Project and Exhibition Files, 1970-2015 (0.5 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1950-2015 (1.6 linear feet; Box 3-4, OV 6, 0.213 GB; ER01)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1955-circa 1956 (0.3 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 2006 (1 folder; OV 7)
Series 8: Photographic Material, circa 1955-2015 (0.5 linear feet; Box 5, OV 8)
Series 9: Unprocessed Addition, circa 1967-2020 (0.4 linear feet; Box 9)
Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Steinberg, Leo; Lax, Robert; Alloway, Lawrence, 1926-1990
- Biographical Material, 1957-2014; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material dates from 1957 to 2014 and includes address books, agendas, an autograph book from summer camp, school documents, interviews, and a resume.
  - Address Books, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agendas, 1970-1971; 1979; 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autograph Book, Camp Taum Sauk, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Certificates and Diplomas, 1963; 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Grades, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interview with Goldring by Beatyrice Colormina, Transcripts, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview with Goldring by Unknown Interviewer for Museum in Beijing, China, Transcripts, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Resume, 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1962-2015; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.2 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Correspondence dates from 1962-2015 and is personal and professional in nature. Found here are letters, emails, postcards, holiday cards, invitations, and exhibition announcements from friends, some of whom Goldring met while traveling in Italy. Notable correspondents include Leo Steinberg whom Goldring studied with at New York University, and Robert Lax, whose letters include many poems. Also included is one letter from Lawrence Alloway. Letters and postcards sent to the Goldring family while Goldring was in Europe provide frequent and detailed descriptions of her travels. Professional correspondence is with galleries, museums, colleges, and others regarding exhibitions, articles, teaching positions, and other opportunities. The first folder includes an index created by Goldring identifying each correspondent.
  - Correspondent Index, 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lawrence Alloway, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alessandro Anselmi, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1983; 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Paolo Barbero, 2005-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - H. Stafford Bryant, circa 1970-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jack Burnham, 1971-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 2006-2015; 1978-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Dennis Crompton, 2009-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Roger Cutforth, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 2002-2015; 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Massimo d'Alessandro, 1984-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1977-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Carlos Estevez, 2001-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 2011-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Heiner Gimmler, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 2008-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ed Hill and Suzanne Bloom, 1990-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 2010-2015; 1976-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Robert Kaupelis, 1979-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Udo Kultermann, 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - K, Miscellaneous, circa 2000-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Robert Lax, 1978-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Gianni Martini, 2010-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 2009-2014; circa 1970-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1977; 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 2014-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Jeffrey Paine, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1978-1979; 2011-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - James Rosen, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Anne Markham Schulz, 1968-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Leo Steinberg, 1970s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - David Levi Strauss, 1998-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1970s; 2005-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Michael Taussig, 2009-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Jay Tolson, circa 1980-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Michael Webb, 1978-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jeff Weiss, 2012-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Peter Lamborn Wilson, circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - V, Miscellaneous, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing, Letters to Goldring Family from Israel, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Outgoing, Letters to Goldring Family from Italy, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Outgoing, Postcards to Goldring Family from Italy and Europe, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Surname or Sender Unidentified, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1967; 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Professional Correspondence, 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Professional Correspondence, 2010s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters Regarding Goldring's Work, circa 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Writings, circa 1955-2014; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2
  Writings date from circa 1955-2014 and consist of published articles and exhibition reviews, two travel diaries, a lecture, an essay written while a student at New York University, and several writings from adolescence, which include illustrated stories and literary papers. The last folder holds a writing by Jay Tolson about Goldring's work.
  - Articles, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Articles for Italian Magazine PresS/Tletter, 2009-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Articles, 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Travel Diaries, Israel, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Lecture, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Reviews, 2014; 1988; 2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Essay, "After the Curtain Falls," for Leo Steinberg's Criticism Course, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Writings from Adolescence, circa 1955-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Writing by Jay Tolson Regarding Goldring's Work, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Project and Exhibition Files, 1970-2015; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Project and exhibition files date from 1970-2015 and include correspondence, photographic material, proposals, schedules, exhibition plans, and a variety of printed material. Printed material relating to exhibitions without any corresponding primary documents is in Series 5: Printed Material. The folder titled "Montclair State University" relates to the many functions Goldring serves there, including teaching and exhibiting.
  - Project Files, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - SITE (Sculpture in the Environment), 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Montclair State University, 1970-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Set Design for ODE, 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Ellis Island Project, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Fulbright, India and Sri Lanka, 1992-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Files, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Image of the Home (1978), Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies, Nassau County Museum, New York, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Drawings with Foto-Projections (1980), SoHo 20, New York, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Independent American Photography (1980), Poland, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - The Photographer's Hand (1980-1983), Traveling Exhibition, 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Drawings with Foto-Projections (1981), University of Haifa, Israel, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - International Terra 2 (1981), Poland, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Studio in Stromboli (1983), Mississippi Museum of Art, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Recent Works (1988), Drury College, Missouri, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Cibachrome Foto-Projections (1991), Jayne H. Baum Gallery, New York, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Drawings and Foto-Projections (1991), Meridian Gallery, San Francisco, California, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - LEGEND (1991), ALVA Gallery, New London, Connecticut, 1991-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Cibachrome Foto-Projections (1991), Elliot Smith Gallery, St. Louis, Missouri, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Images of Myanmar (1992), Grand Central Terminal, New York, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Distillations (1997), Centre for Photography as an Art-Form, Mumbai, India, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Diverse Visions//photographic perspectives (1997), Pittsburgh Center for the Arts, Pennsylvania, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Eye of the Beholder (1997), International Center of Photography, New York, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Distillations: Re-Visiting South Asia (2001), Southeast Museum of Photography, Daytona Beach Community College, Florida, 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Isurumuniya (2003), Bratislava, Slovakia, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Palimpsest (2006), Various Iterations, 2004-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Printed Material, circa 1950-2015; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.6 Linear feet Box 3-4, OV 6; 0.213 Gigabytes ER01
  Printed material dates from circa 1950 to 2015 and includes clippings, ephemera, exhibition material, lecture announcements, periodicals, postcards, yearbooks, and posters. Ephemera is primarily from Goldring's adolescence and includes programs from high school and commencements. Exhibition material includes announcements, brochures, press, and exhibition catalogs relating to exhibitions Goldring participated in, curated, or juried. One exhibition catalog is in digital format. Periodicals are primarily magazines and journals featuring Goldring's work or reviews of her work. Goldring's postcard collection has been assembled during the course of her world travel.
  - Clippings, circa 1950-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ephemera, 1958-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Material, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Material, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Exhibition Material, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
  - Exhibition Material, 2000s; Archival Resource Key; Includes born-digital materials, see ER01 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Snapshot, An Exhibition of 1,000 Artists, Contemporary Museum, Baltimore, MD (November 2000-January 2001), Digital Photographs and Documents, Archival Resource Key; 0.213 Gigabytes One computer file See the READ ME file to access contents. (Folder ER01)
  - Exhibition Material, 2010s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Lecture Announcements, 1984-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Periodicals, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Periodicals, 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Periodicals, 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Periodicals, 2010s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Postcards, 1960s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Yearbooks, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Posters, 1981-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 6)
- Scrapbooks, 1955-circa 1956; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 4
  Two scrapbooks from Goldring's adolescence date from 1955 and circa 1956. One is titled "Sixth Grade Memories," and contains drawings and signatures from classmates. The other is untitled and incorporates a variety of printed material and ephemera. Many items are not affixed to the page, but placed in between the pages.
  - Scrapbook, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Sixth Grade Memories", circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Artwork, circa 2006; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 1 Folder OV 7
  Artwork dates from circa 2006 and includes preliminary sketches and photographic collages.
  - Sketches and Test Prints, circa 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box OV 7)
- Photographic Material, circa 1955-2015; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 5, OV 8
  Photographic material is primarily photographs and copy prints, with a few slides of the World Trade Center on September 11, 2001 and Goldring's close friend Robert Lax. Goldring has organized the photographs into "packets" A-G and has provided a detailed inventory of each packet. Found here are many images of Golding throughout all stages of her life, with friends, traveling, working, and at exhibition openings. "Packet F" includes copy prints of family photographs from the early twentieth century.
  - "Packet A", 1973-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Packet B", 1961-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Packet C", 1982-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Packet D", 2005-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Packet E", 1965-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Packet F", 1956-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Oversized material housed in OV 8
  - "Packet G", circa 2000s-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Photo Album, Birch Trail Camp, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Robert Lax, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Oversize "Packet F," from Box 5, Folder 6, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 8)
- Unprocessed Addition, circa 1967-2020; Series 9; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet
  - Unprocessed Papers, circa 1967-2020; Archival Resource Key (Box 9)